Guide to the History of Medicine Picture File, 1523-2002 and undated RL.00570
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- History of Medicine Picture File: Subjects Series, approx. 487 items
  - Physicians, 37 items
    - "Beaumont and St. Martin," color print reproduction of painting by Dean Norwell, 20th century, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 16, Folder 6)
      Shows Dr. Beaumont, Army surgeon, in his home at Fort Mackinack, 1820s, as he collects gastric fluid from patient St. Martin's fistula, with wife and child present in room.
    - "A student's dream," print reproduction of early 20th century black-and-white photograph, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 16, Folder 6)
      A physician is lying asleep on examination table, surrounded by skeletons in the role of physicians/examiners.
    - Facsimile of physician's oath, Hebrew manuscript text, circa 6th century AD, published in 1952, box size: 18.5 x 24 inches (Box 17, Folder 7)
      Physician's oath, found at the end of a medical work by Asaph the physician, who lived in Israel in 6th century AD. Facsimile of original Oxford Hebrew Ms 2138. Text is reproduced in Hebrew script on one side and in English on the other. Red initial letters. Matted with two windows.
    - [Physician, woman, and skeleton], color lithograph or etching, circa 1920s, box size: 18.5 x 24 inches (Box 17, Folder 7)
      Image of physician or surgeon in white coat with cap, supporting a nude woman with long hair, pushes away a skeleton who is kneeling and grasping her by the legs. Signed by unidentified artist.
    - "The doctor and his patient," photograph of painting by Gerard Dou (1613-1675), undated, box size: 23 x 30 inches (Box 18, Folder 8)
      Carbon print photograph of painting, from Royal Gallery of Buckingham Palace. Physician in fur hat and robes gazes upward at liquid in glass globe, while holding wrist of female patient, also in fur-trimmed garments.
    - "Le paralitique servy [sic] par ses enfans / The paralytic served by his children. Presented to the Earle of [Sweting?], by his most obedient servant [Cartiche?]," engraving, circa late 18th century, box size: 23 x 30 inches (Box 18, Folder 9)
      Engraving after painting by Greuze. An old man on his sickbed is served food and drink by his many children.
    - "La malade," photograph of 1894 painting by Gabriel Metsu, undated, box size: 23 x 30 inches (Box 18, Folder 9)
      Carbon print photograph of painting, from the Hermitage at St. Petersburg. Portrait of sick woman in fur-trimmed garments, seated in large chair, while physician in black robes to her right gazes at liquid in glass globe.
    - "Sancho at the feast starved by his physician," by William Hogarth, engraved by T. Cook, black-and-white, circa 1812, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - "Vaccination," color reproduction of 19th century painting by Dagnant-Bouveret, 20th century, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Postcards, 7 items
    - Porcelain figures, undated, from The Wellcome Historical Medical Museum, London, color postcards, 20th century (Box 12, Folder 34)
      Subjects include Meissen figures of Florence Nightingale, a gout sufferer,a quack doctor, a faun and baby, and alchemy.
  - Psychology and Morality, 4 items
    - "The four stages of cruelty," four engravings by Cook, after William Hogarth, London, 1799, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 16, Folder 9)
      Four engravings by T. Cook from Hogarth's designs: "First stage of cruelty," "Second stage of cruelty," "Cruelty in perfection," and "The reward of cruelty."
      The detailed scenes depict a fictional character's progressive cruelty to animals, leading to murder, hanging, and a grisly end on a dissection table. Around the central character in each engraving are shown many other acts of cruelty by other individuals, with numerous symbolic elements.
  - Surgery, 20 items
    - Surgeon operating on a soldier, Walther Hermann Ryff, Frankfurt, engraving, circa 1541 (Box 12, Folder 35)
      From "Stadt und Feldtbuch." Man treats another's head wound while another man with arm in a sling stands by; a battle rages in the background. Date is taken from penciled note.
    - Barber-surgeon operating behind a man's ear, Lucas van Leyden, small engraving mounted on modern paper leaf, circa 1523/1524 (Box 12, Folder 35)
      From "Bades-Chirurg."
    - "Der barbier/The barber," engraving, Stahlstich von Carse, after Brouwer, circa 1840 (Box 12, Folder 35)
      A barber-surgeon operates on a man's arm; an onlooker stands nearby. Original painting is by Adriaen Brouwer.
    - "L'homme à la fourchette," M.Lasseur, engraving, circa 1885 (Box 12, Folder 35)
      From Hygiène et médecine des deux sexes. Surgeon operates on a man who has swallowed a fork. Shows two inset views of patient and stomach with fork inside. Drawing by Stablo.
    - Surgeon operating on top of screaming patient's head, from Rotterdam Museum, Frans Hals (?), small sepia photo reproduction of painting, undated (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - "Operation on an arm," original work by Flemish painter Adriaen Brouwer (1605-1638), lithograph?, early 20th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - "O Barbeiro da Aldêa," Portuguese engraving of work by Adriaen Brouwer, 19th century?, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - "Ether Day," modern color photographic reproduction of 19th century painting buy Robert Hinckley, undated, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 14)
      Image portrays first surgery performed in the U.S. with ether as anaesthetic, at Massachusetts General Hospital; modern color glossy reproduction of large painting by Hinckley, completed in 1893.
    - Surgery scenes from the 18th through the 20th centuries, black-and-white glossy mounted photographs, after 1940, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 14)
      Note on back reads "Trent Oct. Surg Cli [or Clin]" (Duke University).
    - "Wm. T. G. Morton, M.D., Boston, making the first public demonstration of etherization at the Massachusetts General Hospital surrounded by the medical staff of that institution," engraving by H.B. Hall, 19th century, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 14, Folder 14)
      Accompanied by an engraved broadside invitation to the 50th anniversary commemoration of the first public demonstration of anaesthesia at Massachusetts General Hospital, October 16th, 1896.
    - "Telephe guéri par la rouille du même fer dont il a êté blessé" [Telephus cured by the same blade that wounded him], B. Picart, black-and-white engraving, 1730, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - "Heelmeester" and "Kopster" [cupping and lancing of a boil (?)], two black-and-white engravings, Dutch(?), 1695, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Atelier de réparation [plastic surgeon's operating room - one woman in front of mirror held by nurse, while another woman's empty skin is being sewn up by assistant], G. Hoffmany, color lithograph, circa 1920s, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 7)
      Two copies, one matted; one appears to be signed by artist.
    - "The dawn of abdominal surgery," color lithographic reproduction of painting by Dean Norwell, 20th century, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 16, Folder 7)
      Shows tableau with Dr. Ephraim McDowell, getting ready to perform ovariotomy, interior of frontier cabin with assistants and husband attending, Danville, Kentucky, 1809.
    - The history of anaesthesia, posters, circa 1944, box size: 23 x 30 inches; 4 items (Box 18, Folder 10)
      Black-and-white "study charts" numbered 1 to 4, with many illustrations and text explicating the history of anesthesia; central inset advertises the 1944 Paramount Pictures film The Great Moment, about the Boston dentist W.T.G. Morton who first used anesthesia.
  - Surgical Instruments, 34 items
    - Bronze Roman surgical instruments, circa 3rd century A.D., modern black-and-white photograph (Box 12, Folder 36)
      From the History of Medicine Artifacts Collection.
    - Saw and trephine, modern black-and-white photographs, 6 items (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - "Chirurgie," partially bound engravings of medical instruments, sometimes with human figures illustrating use, with large engraved frontispiece and index to illustrations, 18th century, box size: 16x20 inches; 36 items (Box 16, Folder 8)
      Illustrations were originally published by Denis Diderot and Jean D'Alembert around 1770 (online source).
    - "Chirurgie," copy of plate 35 from above, 18th century, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 8)
      Penciled note on item gives date as 1786.
  - Tourniquets, 3 items
    - Tourniquet, black-and-white and color photographs, 20th century (Box 12, Folder 36)
      Includes three photographs, one color and two black-and-white.
  - Urine, 2 items
    - "Urine Man," "A Doctor of Medicine," Magdalen College, engraving, 1508, reproduction print of photograph on card stock, 20th century (Box 12, Folder 37)
      Also includes one negative.
  - Trent Collection, 4 items
    - Dr. Josiah Trent's reading room, taken at Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans' house before move to Duke Medical Center Library, black-and-white photographs, 1956, 4 items (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - X-rays, 2 items
    - U.S. Army portable X-ray truck, black-and-white photographs, 1918, 2 items (Box 12, Folder 39)
      Photographs measure 2x3 inches and are housed in an envelope labeled "X-ray repair shop, Paris."